Guide to the Human Rights Watch records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Human Rights Watch records,
1978-1997
[Bulk Dates: 1989-1994]
Human Rights Watch (Organization). Middle East and North Africa Division.
36.25 linear ft. (29 record cartons)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
HR#0002
7749013
History
This record group contains the records of the United States based Middle East and North Africa Watch, a division of the human rights organization, Human Rights Watch.
Materials include analytical papers, correspondence, memorandums, monitoring reports, news clippings, newsletters, and publications.
These materials document the issues effecting the Arab world during this period. To illustrate, the Gulf War and its after effects in Iraq, Kuwait and the United States are covered in detail. This record group contains the results of fact-finding missions documenting UN humanitarian operations in the Western Sahara and monitoring human rights abuses in the Arab world.
Scope and Content
Materials include correspondence and e-mail communications, mission reports, testimonies and interviews, addresses and contact lists, confidential interoffice memos, legal and advocacy material, internal planning and policy material, declassified government and United Nations documents, published and unpublished human rights reports from individuals and fellow NGOs, press clippings and news releases, and maps. Another category of documents consists of HRW reports and briefing papers, as well as press releases and open letters to heads of state, governments and various government agencies.
Materials related to missions contain unpublished information on sources, cases, and the state of affairs in various countries. They include professional and personal mission notes taken by country researchers and monitors during investigative field trips, testimonies by and interviews with victims of various human rights abuses, pre-mission and post-mission memos, material on research methodology, correspondence and e-mail communications, addresses and contact lists.
Thematically, these documents cover the various major military and political upheavals occurring in the Middle East and North Africa during the early to middle 1990s. The papers also comprise such human rights initiatives as attempting to bring a case against Iraq at the International Court of Justice, the campaigns to promote freedom of expression, and the rights of women in the region.
Arrangement
This Record Group is arranged into 6 series
Series I: Andrew Whitley, Director, 1978-1995
Series II: Aziz Abu Hamad, Associate, Director, 1984-1995
Series III: Julie Friedman, 1978-1992
Series IV: Eric Goldstein, Research Director, 1986-1997
Series V: Virginia N. Sherry, Associate Director, 1989-1993
Series VI: Publications, 1989-1991
Subjects
Human Rights Watch (Organization); Iran--Foreign relations--United States.; Iran--Refugees.; Israel--Boundaries--Arab countries.; Israel--Defenses.; Israel--Foreign relations--Arab countries; Kuwait--Economic conditions--1991-; Lebanon--History--1990-; United States--Foreign relations--1989-; United States--Foreign relations--Kuwait.; Arab-Israeli conflict--1993-; Freedom of expression--Iran; Human rights--Bahrain.; Human rights--Iran.; Human rights--Iraq--Kurdistān.; Human rights--Syria.; Iraq-Kuwait Crisis, 1990-1991.; Kurds--Civil rights--Iraq.; Kurds--Crimes against--Iraq.; Kurds--Legal status, laws, etc.--Syria.; Non-governmental organizations--Iraq.; Opposition (Political science)--Iran.; Palestinian Arabs--Civil rights--Israel.; Persian Gulf War, 1991.; Prisons--Israel.; Torture--Bahrain.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. Please consult the Rare Book and Manuscript Library for further information.
The HRW Records are restricted. Access to the HRW Records may only be granted with the written permission of HRW.
Acquisition
Human Rights Watch Deposit 2006
This material was originally deposited at the University of Colorado at Boulder by Human Rights Watch in the 1990s. The material was deposited with the Rare Book and Manuscript Library in 2006.
Finding aid in repository; folder-level control.
Online finding aid available.
- Series 1: Andrew Whitley, Director, 1978-1995
  - Subseries 1: Country Files, 1978-1995
    - Afghanistan (Box 611)
      - Background, 1990-1991 (Box 611, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 611, Folder 2)
      - Prison Conditions, undated (Box 611, Folder 3)
      - Report--Human Rights Watch--Middle East Watch, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 611, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Egypt--Government, 1990-1991 (Box 611, Folder 6)
    - Iran
      - Arabha, Naser (editor, Farad magazine), 1992 (Box 611, Folder 7)
      - Arms
        - Development, 1993 (Box 611, Folder 8)
        - Sales, 1991-1993 (Box 611, Folder 9)
      - Baraheni, Reza (poet, writer), 1992 (Box 611, Folder 10)
      - Beizei, Bahram (film maker)--Interview, 1993 (Box 611, Folder 11)
      - Committee for the Defence of Political Prisioners in Iran--The Iranian Bulletins, 1979 (Box 611, Folder 12)
      - Elections, 1993 (Box 611, Folder 13)
      - Donya-ye Sokhan, 1993 (Box 611, Folder 14)
      - Firouz, Miriam, 1991-1992 (Box 611, Folder 15)
      - Foreign Relations
        - Bosnia, 1992-1993 (Box 611, Folder 16)
        - European Community, 1993 (Box 611, Folder 17)
      - Foroohar, Kambriz (journalist), 1988-1989 (Box 611, Folder 18)
      - Freedom of Expression
        - Censorship
          - Analysis, 1993 (Box 611, Folder 19)
          - Books, 1991-1993 (Box 611, Folder 20)
          - Domestic Press, 1991-1995 (Box 611, Folder 21)
          - Export of Iranian Publications, 1993 (Box 611, Folder 22)
          - 50 Iranian Intellectuals in Support of Salman Rushdie, 1992-1993 (Box 611, Folder 23)
          - Film
            - General, 1992-1993 (Box 611, Folder 24)
            - Veiled Threat, 1989-1992 (Box 611, Folder 25)
          - Foreign Correspondents, 1990-1993 (Box 611, Folder 26)
        - General, 1992-1993, (2 Folders) (Box 611, Folder 27 to 28)
        - Government Commentary, 1991-1992 (Box 611, Folder 29)
        - Intellectual Freedom, undated (Box 611, Folder 30)
        - Majles (Iranian legislative body), 1992 (Box 611, Folder 31)
        - Mass Movement, undated (Box 611, Folder 32)
        - Mohammad Khatami--Resignation, 1992 (Box 611, Folder 33)
        - Mojahdin--Reaction to Galindo Pohl’s Report, 1990 (Box 611, Folder 34)
        - Pahlavi Dynasty (1941-1979), 1978, 1990 (Box 611, Folder 35)
        - Persecutions--General, 1989-1992 (Box 611, Folder 36)
        - Political, 1987-1993 (Box 611, Folder 37)
        - Publishing Houses, 1990-1993 (Box 611, Folder 38)
        - Students, 1991-1993 (Box 611, Folder 39)
        - Theatre, 1992 (Box 611, Folder 40)
      - Golestan, Kaveh (photojournalist), 1993 (Box 611, Folder 41)
      - Heydari, Salman (journalist), 1992 (Box 611, Folder 42)
      - Human Rights
        - Perception, 1990-1993 (Box 611, Folder 43)
        - Reports, 1992-1993 (Box 611, Folder 44)
        - Statements, 1993 (Box 611, Folder 45)
      - Human Rights Organizations
        - Center for Monitoring Political Imprisonment in Iran, undated (Box 611, Folder 46)
        - Council to Monitor Human Rights in Iran, 1987 (Box 611, Folder 47)
        - International Committee for the Defense of Human Rights, 1981 (Box 611, Folder 48)
        - League for the Defense of Human Rights in Tehran, undated (Box 611, Folder 49)
        - Ligue pour ;a Defense des Droits de l’Homme en Iran, 1991, 1993 (Box 611, Folder 50)
        - National Campaign for Democracy and Human Rights in Iran, 1989-1990 (Box 611, Folder 51)
        - Organization for Defending Victims of Violence, 1990, 1992 (Box 611, Folder 52)
      - Internal Conflict--Khamenei-Rafsanjani, 1992-1993 (Box 612, Folder 1)
      - Iran Project
        - Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 612, Folder 2)
        - Finances, 1991 (Box 612, Folder 3)
          [RESTRICTED UNTIL 2067
        - General, 1990 (Box 612, Folder 4)
          [RESTRICTED UNTIL 2066]
        - Research Boroujerdi, Mehrzad (researcher) 1990-1991 (Box 612, Folder 5)
          [RESTRICTED UNTIL 2067]
      - Judicial System, 1992-1993 (Box 612, Folder 6)
      - Khaksar, Nasim (poet)--Application, 1993 (Box 612, Folder 7)
        [RESTRICTED UNTIL 2069]
      - Lahidji, Abdol Karim (human rights leader), 1990 (Box 612, Folder 8)
      - Maroufi, Abbas--Editor, Gardoon--Interview, 1993 (Box 612, Folder 9)
      - Mohammedi, Malakeh (editor, journalist), 1991 (Box 612, Folder 10)
      - Mojahedin
        - General, 1987-1992 (Box 612, Folder 11)
        - Hostages, 1992 (Box 612, Folder 12)
        - Press Releases, 1990-1993, (2 Folders) (Box 612, Folder 13 to 14)
        - United States--Support, 1992-1993 (Box 612, Folder 15)
      - Naderpour, Nader (poet)--Application, 1992-1993 (Box 612, Folder 16)
      - Opposition Groups
        - Flag of Freedom Organization of Iran, 1990-1991 (Box 612, Folder 17)
        - Freedom Movement, 1990-1991 (Box 612, Folder 18)
        - General, 1992 (Box 612, Folder 19)
        - Political Groups, 1989-1992 (Box 612, Folder 20)
        - Reza Pahlavi II, 1990 (Box 612, Folder 21)
        - Tudeh Party, 1989-1990 (Box 612, Folder 22)
      - Parsipour, Shahrnoush (novelist), 1992-1993 (Box 612, Folder 23)
      - Political Prisoners
        - Amir-Entezam, Abbas, 1992 (Box 612, Folder 24)
        - Saedi, Gholam-Hoseyn, 1986 (Box 612, Folder 25)
        - General, 1990-1993 (Box 612, Folder 26)
      - Prisoners of War (POWs)
        - General, 1993 (Box 612, Folder 27)
        - Iranian--Civilian, 1993 (Box 612, Folder 28)
        - Iraqi, 1992-1993 (Box 612, Folder 29)
        - Zadeh, Sharif, (Iranian POW), 1982-1987 (Box 612, Folder 30)
      - Ravanipour, Moniroo (novelist), 1993 (Box 612, Folder 31)
      - Refugees
        - Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 612, Folder 32)
        - Danish Refugee Council, 1991-1992 (Box 612, Folder 33)
        - Iran--Located in, 1993 (Box 612, Folder 34)
        - Iranian
          - General, 1992-1993 (Box 612, Folder 35)
          - Turkey, 1992-1993 (Folder 36)
            - Deported from, 1992-1993 (Box 612, Folder 37)
        - Report--Middle East Watch, 1991 (Box 612, Folder 38)
      - Riots and Executions, 1992 (Box 612, Folder 39)
      - Rushdie, Salman (writer)
        - General, 1989-1993, (2 Folders) (Box 612, Folder 40 to 41)
        - Letter Project (1993), 1992-1993 (Box 612, Folder 42)
      - Saidi-Sirjani, Ali Akbar (journalist, poet)--Interview, 1992-1993 (Box 612, Folder 43)
      - Shamlu, Ahmad (journalist, poet)--Application, 1990-1993 (Box 612, Folder 44)
      - Soltanpour, Sayid (playwright, poet), 1981 (Box 612, Folder 45)
      - Speeches, 1993 (Box 612, Folder 46)
      - Domestic Unrest, 1993 (Box 613, Folder 1)
      - Drug Trafficking, 1989-1993 (Box 613, Folder 2)
      - Foreign Relations--United States
        - General, 1989-1993 (Box 613, Folder 3)
        - Hostages, 1988-1991 (Box 613, Folder 4)
        - Iran Contra, 1991 (Box 613, Folder 5)
        - U.S. State Department Reports, 1993 (Box 613, Folder 6)
      - Imports--‘dual-use’, 1993 (Box 613, Folder 7)
      - Interviews Notes, 1989-1992, (6 Folders) (Box 613, Folder 8 to 13)
        [RESTRICTED UNTIL 2068]
      - United Nations--Reports, 1990-1993, (2 Folders) (Box 613, Folder 14 to 15)
      - U.S.–Iran Review, 1993 (Box 613, Folder 16)
      - Weapons--Nuclear, 1992-1993 (Box 613, Folder 17)
    - Iraq
      - Al-Hakim, Sayed Mohanned Baqir--Family, 1988-1991 (Box 613, Folder 18)
      - Amnesties--Granted, 1990-1991 (Box 613, Folder 19)
      - Amnesty International, 1986-1991 (Box 613, Folder 20)
      - Arrests, Detentions, Torture, 1989-1990 (Box 613, Folder 21)
      - Bazoft, Farzad
        - Press Clippings, 1990 (Box 613, Folder 22)
        - Protest Letters, 1990 (Box 613, Folder 23)
        - Reports Amnesty International, 1989-1990 (Box 613, Folder 24)
        - Statements Governmental, 1990 (Box 613, Folder 25)
      - Case Studies, 1990-1991 (Box 613, Folder 26)
      - Chemical Weapons, 1988-1992 (Box 613, Folder 27)
      - Children--Treatment of, 1989-1991 (Box 613, Folder 28)
      - Citizens--Travel--Right of, 1990-1991 (Box 613, Folder 29)
      - Citizenship, undated (Box 613, Folder 30)
      - Civilian Structures, 1991 (Box 613, Folder 31)
      - Economy, 1990-1991 (Box 613, Folder 32)
      - Embargo
        - Legal Aspects, 1990 (Box 613, Folder 33)
        - Reaction
          - Arab, 1990 (Box 613, Folder 34)
          - Iraqi, 1990 (Box 613, Folder 35)
          - World, 1990, 1992 (Box 613, Folder 36)
        - Result of, 1990 (Box 613, Folder 37)
        - U.N. Security Council--Support of, 1990 (Box 613, Folder 38)
        - U.S. Involvement, 1990 (Box 613, Folder 39)
      - Executions
        - General, 1989-1991 (Box 613, Folder 40)
        - Radwaniyya Detention Centre, 1993 (Box 613, Folder 41)
      - Foreign Broadcast Information Service (FBIS), 1991-1993, (4 Folders) (Box 613, Folder 42 to 45)
      - Foreign Relations (Box 614)
        - Arab Countries, 1990 (Box 614, Folder 1)
        - General, 1988-1991 (Box 614, Folder 2)
        - Iran, 1991 (Box 614, Folder 3)
      - Freedom of Expression, 1987-1991 (Box 614, Folder 4)
      - General--Statistics, 1988-1992, (2 Folders) (Box 614, Folder 5 to 6)
      - Gulf War (1991)
        - Anti-Semitism, 1991 (Box 614, Folder 7)
        - Arab-Americans, 1991 (Box 614, Folder 8)
        - Casualties--Civilian
          - El-Ameriyya, 1991 (Box 614, Folder 9)
          - Amman-Bagdad Road, 1991 (Box 614, Folder 10)
          - General, 1991 (Box 614, Folder 11)
          - Infrastructure-Iraqi Society, 1991 (Box 614, Folder 12)
        - Casualties--Military, 1991 (Box 614, Folder 13)
        - Censorship, 1991 (Box 614, Folder 14)
        - Ecological Issues, 1991 (Box 614, Folder 15)
        - Israel, 1990-1991 (Box 614, Folder 16)
        - Journalists, 1990-1991 (Box 614, Folder 17)
        - Legal Issues, 1990-1991 (Box 614, Folder 18)
        - Middle East Watch, 1990 (Box 614, Folder 19)
        - Military Events, 1990-1991, (2 Folders) (Box 614, Folder 20 to 21)
        - Peace Negotiations, 1990-1991 (Box 614, Folder 22)
        - Post-War Conditions, 1991-1992, (2 Folders) (Box 614, Folder 23 to 24)
        - Statements
          - Iraqi, 1990-1991 (Box 614, Folder 25)
          - United States, 1990-1991, (2 Folders) (Box 614, Folder 26 to 27)
        - U.N. Sanctions, 1990-1991 (Box 614, Folder 28)
        - War Crimes, 1991 (Box 614, Folder 29)
      - Human Rights
        - Committee for the Defence of Human Rights in Iraq, 1990-1991 (Box 614, Folder 30)
        - Documental Center for Human Rights in Iraq, 1990-1991, (2 Folders) (Box 614, Folder 31 to 32)
        - General Conditions, 1985-1990 (Box 614, Folder 33)
        - Opposition Groups-General, 1990 (Box 614, Folder 34)
        - Organizations, 1991 (Box 614, Folder 35)
        - Testimony, 1992 (Box 614, Folder 36)
        - Violations
          - Report: Islamic Association for Human Rights, 1990 (Box 614, Folder 37)
          - Report: Islamic Association in France, 1986 April (Box 615, Folder 1)
      - Humanitarian Efforts, 1990-1992 (Box 615, Folder 2)
      - Hussein, Saddam (President of Iraq)--Profile, 1988-1992, (2 Folders) (Box 615, Folder 3 to 4)
      - International Law, 1990 (Box 615, Folder 5)
      - Iran-Iraq War (1980-1988)
        - Aftermath, 1990-1991 (Box 615, Folder 6)
        - Analysis, 1988-1990 (Box 615, Folder 7)
        - Civilian Casualties, 1988 (Box 615, Folder 8)
        - Military Events, 1988-1990 (Box 615, Folder 9)
        - Peace Proposals, 1988-1991 (Box 615, Folder 10)
        - POWs
          - General, 1988-1992 (Box 615, Folder 11)
          - International Committee of the Red Cross, 1980-1988 (Box 615, Folder 12)
          - Statements, 1990 (Box 615, Folder 13)
      - Islamic Conference, 1990 (Box 615, Folder 14)
      - Journalists--Federation of Arab Journalists, undated (Box 615, Folder 15)
      - Kurds--Operation Anfal (1986-1989)
        - Report, 1988 (Box 615, Folder 16)
        - Research Materials, 1988-1992, (2 Folders) (Box 615, Folder 17 to 18)
        - Statements--Iraqi Government, 1987-1992 (Box 615, Folder 19)
      - Kuwait Invasion (1990)
        - Economic Effects, 1990 (Box 615, Folder 20)
        - Statements--Arab, 1990 (Box 615, Folder 21)
        - Summit--Arab, 1990 (Box 615, Folder 22)
      - Middle East Watch (Box 615)
        - Reports, 1990-1992, (3 Folders) (Box 615, Folder 23 to 25)
    - Mission--Iran
      - Memoranda, 1991 (Box 615, Folder 26)
      - Notes, 1991 (Box 615, Folder 27)
    - Politics--Internal, 1988-1991 (Box 615, Folder 28)
    - Kurds (Box 616)
      - Clashes with Iraqis, 1991-1992 (Box 616, Folder 1)
      - Conversation Notes and Interviews, 1988-1992 (Box 616, Folder 2)
        [RESTRICTED UNTIL 2068
      - Elections, 1992 (Box 616, Folder 3)
      - Eyewitness Account, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 4)
      - General, 1989-1992, (2 Folders) (Box 616, Folder 5 to 6)
      - Genocide, 1988-1992 (Box 616, Folder 7)
      - Human Rights Center, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 8)
      - Press References, 1992 (Box 616, Folder 9)
      - Report--Post-war, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 10)
      - Unquiet Graves--Drafts, 1992 (Box 616, Folder 11)
      - United States
        - Involvement, 1988-1992 (Box 616, Folder 12)
        - Relations, 1991-1993 (Box 616, Folder 13)
      - Winds of Death: Iraq’s Use of Poison Gas Against Its Kurdish Population, 1989 December (Box 616, Folder 14)
    - Kuwait
      - Invasion, 1990 (Box 616, Folder 15)
      - Looting, 1990-1991 (Box 616, Folder 16)
      - Pre-War Relations with Iraq, 1990 (Box 616, Folder 17)
      - Post-Invasion Relations with Iraq, 1990-1991 (Box 616, Folder 18)
    - Labor Rights, 1989 (Box 616, Folder 19)
    - Middle East Mirror, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 20)
    - Military
      - Nuclear, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 21)
      - Opposition, 1990-1991 (Box 616, Folder 22)
      - Pre-Invasion, 1990 (Box 616, Folder 23)
      - Post-Invasion, 1990-1991 (Box 616, Folder 24)
    - Minorities, 1988-1991 (Box 616, Folder 25)
    - NGOs and Relief Organizations, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 26)
    - Opposition
      - Groups, 1986 (Box 616, Folder 27)
      - Gulf War, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 28)
      - Post-War, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 29)
    - POWs, 1991
      - Allied
        - Release, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 30)
        - Troops, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 31)
      - General, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 32)
      - Middle East Watch--Work, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 33)
      - Treatment--Gulf War, 1991 (Box 616, Folder 34)
    - Prisons, 1991-1992 (Box 616, Folder 35)
    - Post-Invasion Reaction to External Pressure to Withdraw, 1990 (Box 617, Folder 1)
    - Public Documents, 1990 (Box 617, Folder 2)
    - Refugees (Box 617)
      - General, 1991 (Box 617, Folder 3)
      - Jordon-Iraq Border, 1991 (Box 617, Folder 4)
      - Post-Invasion, 1990 (Box 617, Folder 5)
      - UN Disaster Relief Organization (UNDRO), 1991 (Box 617, Folder 6)
    - Regional Protests--Gulf, 1991 (Box 617, Folder 7)
    - Religion
      - Assyrian Christians, 1989-1992 (Box 617, Folder 8)
      - Parties, 1991 (Box 617, Folder 9)
      - Yezidis, 1993 (Box 617, Folder 10)
    - Reports
      - Air War: Unanswered Questions, 1991 (Box 617, Folder 11)
      - Congress: Send a Message on Iraqi Oppression, 1989 (Box 617, Folder 12)
    - Shahristani, Dr. Hussein, 1991-1992 (Box 617, Folder 13)
    - Suppression of Islamic Opposition, 1990-1992 (Box 617, Folder 14)
    - Supreme Council for the Islamic Revolution in Iraq, 1993 (Box 617, Folder 15)
    - Terrorism--Post Invasion, 1990-1991 (Box 617, Folder 16)
    - United Nations
      - Commission on Human Rights, 1993 (Box 617, Folder 17)
      - General Assembly
        - Human Rights in Iraq, 1991-1992 (Box 617, Folder 18)
        - Reports, 1992 (Box 617, Folder 19)
      - High Commissioner for Refugees, 1991 (Box 617, Folder 20)
      - Inspectors, 1991 (Box 617, Folder 21)
      - Pre-Invasion of Kuwait, 1989-1990 (Box 617, Folder 22)
      - Relations
        - Pre-Gulf Crisis, 1990-1991 (Box 617, Folder 23)
        - Post-War, 1991-1992, (2 Folders) (Box 617, Folder 24 to 25)
      - Sanctions, 1990-1992 (Box 617, Folder 26)
      - Security Council, 1991-1992 (Box 617, Folder 27)
      - Special Rapporteur--Max van der Stoel, 1992-1993 (Box 617, Folder 28)
      - Use of Force, 1990-1991 (Box 617, Folder 29)
    - United States (Box 618)
      - Documents on Relations with Iraq, 1990, (2 Folders) (Box 618, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Gulf War
        - Analysis--Post-War, 1991 (Box 618, Folder 3)
        - Post-Invasion, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 4)
        - U.S. Conduct, 1991 (Box 618, Folder 5)
      - Military Intervention Arms Negotiation, 1991 (Box 618, Folder 6)
      - Political Analysis--Post Invasion, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 7)
      - Reaction to Invasion of Kuwait, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 8)
      - Relations
        - Gulf War, 1991 January-February (Box 618, Folder 9)
        - Post-War, 1991 (Box 618, Folder 10)
      - Sanctions against Iraq, 1991 (Box 618, Folder 11)
    - Uprisings--Northern Iraq, 1991
      - Individual Cases, 1991 (Box 618, Folder 12)
      - Kurdish
        - Rebellion, 1991 March (Box 618, Folder 13)
        - Uprisings, 1991, (3 Folders) (Box 618, Folder 14 to 16)
    - Uprisings--Southern Iraq, 1991
      - Correspondence--General--Marshes, 1993 (Box 618, Folder 17)
      - Press Clippings, 1991 March-August, (3 Folders) (Box 618, Folder 18 to 20)
      - Shiite Clashes, 1991 (Box 618, Folder 21)
      - U.S. Policy, 1991 (Box 618, Folder 22)
  - Subseries 2: Subject Files, 1989-1992
    - Hostages--Western--Post Invasion, 1990
      - Arab Reaction, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 23)
      - Conditions of Captivity, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 24)
      - Foreign Embassies with Hostages, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 25)
      - Foreign Nationals, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 26)
      - Legal Issues, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 27)
      - Middle East Watch (MEW) Reports, 1990 (Folder 28)
        - Negotiations for Release, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 29)
        - Planned Release, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 30)
        - Public Statements, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 31)
        - Sheltering Foreigners, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 32)
        - United States, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 33)
        - Use as Shields, 1990 (Box 618, Folder 34)
      - Women--Treatment of, 1989 (Box 618, Folder 35)
    - Israel--Prisons--Report
      - Comments, 1990-1991 (Box 618, Folder 36)
      - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 618, Folder 37)
      - Draft, undated (Box 618, Folder 38)
      - Morocco--Report--Middle East Watch, 1991 September (Box 618, Folder 39)
      - Syria--Report--Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 618, Folder 40)
    - Middle East Watch (MEW) (Box 619)
      - Board Meetings, 1990-1992 (Box 619, Folder 1)
      - Monitors--Human Rights Watch, 1990 December (Box 619, Folder 2)
      - Press Clippings, 1992 (Box 619, Folder 3)
      - Political Asylum Project
        - Algeria--Political Asylum, 1989-1990 (Box 619, Folder 4)
        - Asylum Case: Sarraj, Dr. Ala, 1991 (Box 619, Folder 5)
        - Egypt--Political Asylum--Correspondence, 1990 (Box 619, Folder 6)
        - General, 1989-1991 (Box 619, Folder 7)
        - Iran, 1989-1991
          - Cases, 1989-1991 (Box 619, Folder 8)
          - General, 1989-1991 (Box 619, Folder 9)
        - Lebanon--Correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box 619, Folder 10)
        - Middle East Watch--Statements for Asylum Cases, 1991 (Box 619, Folder 11)
        - U.S. Policy--Middle East, 1991 (Box 619, Folder 12)
        - Women’s Project--Middle East, 1987-1992 (Box 619, Folder 13)
- Series 2: Aziz Abu Hamad, Associate Director, 1984-1995